this Mastermind or premaster mind is
titled renovate your
body why is
that
because I just bought a little old house
and am renovating it and realized how
many
parallels we have in renovating our
house and renovating our body when we
want to rejuvenate
give us a fresh start get rid
of rotting parts and worn out pattered
parts and rebuild a body for ourselves
that is feeling good strong flexible
and and joyful to live in right a body
that just is your joy not your
burden um
all right a little bit about me I'm
Professor Johanna Sophia of johanna's
raw foods and coaching and of the
rossome life
project and we will hear more about that
next calendar year in
2025 right
now I am renovating my body as I have
renovated my house it's not done yet so
my body still has to wait which is kind
of sad right you can't really let your
body wait until the house is renovated
um it should be the other way around I
should have done more to renovate my
body before doing the work on the house
of course I'm not doing all the work on
the house and that is also a parallel a
little bit too much my background I am
of course a professor not of nutrition
I'm not a medical doctor I'm not a um
nutritionist I am a professor of writing
directing producing film and I am a
certified Waldorf teacher so my
expertise in terms of my certifications
is in education and learning so maybe
that translates to loving to learn I've
always loved to learn so my research in
terms of what really is life on planet
Earth what really is this body that we
have that we inhabit what really is it
that we need to have the best possible
life experience and the best possible
body to have that life
experience and here we have
a person joining
us welcome Mary I am in the
introduction
and have explained that we have
seen only the 22nd announced on the
registration right and I just post
that post that declaration that I'm
doing The Mastermind on the 22nd wanted
to do this preliminary issue in which I
um
explain what this idea of renovation is
all
about so a little bit more to my
background I grew up with a
very weak and flawed body the worst in
sports with a hole in my heart and the
Crooked back and all kinds of issues
tissue that wasn't connected to the
muscle tissue properly so I grew up with
a very flawed renovation needing body um
but it took a long time to really figure
out what this body needs to get to its
maximum ability and of course everybody
has a different level of a maximum
ability so with all these flaw and
weaknesses I did
learn that purpose is number one and
even though in my renovation that is not
necessarily the number one why do you
buy a house well you could start it that
way as well why do you buy a house or an
apartment or a condo or a car for that
matter it has a purpose so that you can
reside what does it
need and let me go into those details a
little bit later a couple of more things
to my background how I got to johanna's
raw foods and the rwome life project and
to this understanding of how biology
works on planet
Earth not just from learning but from
experiencing
real
adversary
events um
20 years ago and some of you may know
this
story I well now 21 years ago to be
exact I had a mini stroke
or people tell me it was a real stroke
never mind I recovered very well from it
that's why I don't call it such a big
event but it was a drastic wakeup call I
was sitting just as I'm sitting here at
a um table actually here I'm sitting at
a
countertop and I was very stressed out
hadn't slept had hardly
eaten was in a very difficult abusive
relationship the highly intelligent man
who was
very
[Music]
um very what's the word what's the word
what have I used to describe
him
conflicted deeply
conflicted um and of course in a
profession that made that conflict worse
and worse because he was an asset as a
secret agent
so and of course I was not supposed to
really know that either
but people like my
get to know those
things I've met several in the meantime
yeah so that is of course a
life
of Lies a life of duality of but not in
a good way duality
of getting to a point where you don't
know what is reality and what is you're
Mak make believe reality because that is
of course the job of an agent who gets
into other countries other people's
Secrets um pretending to be what they
are
not um
so in this difficult relationship which
was a a an interesting learning
experience for myself and I love
learning and understanding all these
layers and layers of The Human
Experience in this world and in this era
where so many more of us are waking up
to what really
happens and the same then became true
for our human
biology I was already eating organic and
eating mostly plant-based and
but I hadn't really
studied
what the building blocks are for the
best biology of our body and for nature
and how it works so anyway I was sitting
at a table and my hand flew up into the
air like that and I was holding on to
the table with the other hand but my
body weight fell backwards and I felt to
the floor with the chair and could no
longer move my mouth was wide open and I
could not shut it um actually a scream
had come out of my
mouth
um and
I sorry that was just a message coming
in I was then laying on the floor
for quite a
while realizing that I was fully
conscious but that I could
not move could not have access to this
body of
mine so I also had an outer body
experience I suppose people would call
that and I was commanding myself to get
back into that body and get back into
there and do what it needed so that this
would never happen again my children
were
still young they were in middle
school and I needed to be there for them
obviously
so that's where I realized I have to do
whatever is necessary for this body to
make it the best it can possibly be to
make it functioning so that it will
never go on strike on me again
and we all know that when we are very
very
stressed our body does all sorts of
things we get back pain we get headaches
we get diarrhea we get stomach aches we
get extrem ordinary
tiredness chronic fatigue we called it
at one point now it's got all kinds of
other names but that happens when we do
not take care of what it really means so
for me that was my biggest wakeup calls
there were others there
were little steps and understandings but
let's just take that as my wakeup call
ask yourself whether you have ever had
such a wake up calling maybe you did not
listen Maybe you did not know where to
go I was lucky that at that time I
already knew that the best nourishment
for the human body and for any life on
planet Earth
is what I'm going to talk
about so back to the house so we are
acquiring a house whether we rent of
buying you know buying is just a little
more involved because we have to do all
the right things why do we buy a house
what is necessary what needs to function
in that house right why do we have a
house we need a roof over our
head what else do we need we need
heat why do we need the roof to protect
us from the weather to protect us
from at some point wild animals
creatures of all kinds even mice if you
will
right I'm laughing because I'm dealing
with with M this
summer where I was staying I'm staying
not in my house right now I'm staying at
a friend's my house it's still not
finished being
renovated um so we need a roof
we need heat to keep our body in a
temperature that is livable for
humans what else do we need in the house
we need Windows we need to let in air we
need to let old air
out we need sunshine to come into the
windows
or be available in the yard if there's a
yard so we need an outdoor
environment around our dwelling as
well um we need in today's world
electricity and of course when we go to
our body we see that electricity is very
very much part of the functioning of the
human body as well we need
water we need fluids of all kinds right
water of course for the human body and
water for the house we need to have have
garbage removal now I want you to think
of all the equivalents for your body
that I'm mentioning here and then we
need regular cleaning still even though
we put all these things in place we need
regular cleaning what happens if we
don't the dust piles up the dirt keratin
piles up um leftovers pile up garbage
starts to sink and etc etc
so with that house or home comes the
responsibility of regular cleaning as
well all right let's translate that to
our
body I'm trying to force myself to just
stick with this example I'm so good at
relating to the entire world and all of
life on planet Earth but let's just
stick
to the
the
symbol or the
example of a house being
renovated so we're moving into this body
we're
born we're getting the first nourishment
we're taking the first breath of course
becomes comes before the
nourishment we're eliminating for the
first time even before we get
nourishment from our mother's
breast
um so there's the garbage
removal then we get
covered so that we
can slowly
learn to get out of the womb which of
course is a very close
environment into the outside environment
so we we get covered we get hugged we
get
held we
fed
and we get
cleaned how does electricity come
in electricity comes in because the
vibrations the electricity that each of
our bodies creat Crees that each living
thing
creates each tree each flower each
cabbage each
animal everything has an electromagnetic
field an
electricity right we need this
electricity and as we are born we need
the electricity from other human beings
preferably our mother and
father um to
to learn how to have a
healthy Vibe a healthy electricity
production because of course this body
also produces its own electromagnetic
field we can measure it these days all
right we need garbage removal not just
do we need to eliminate we need to
remove the garbage out of our house
right out of our environment or to the
yard where it can become fertilizer for
the next forms of life or other forms of
life so that our excrement naturally
would be the fertilizer for the the
plants that then provide our food
again that is the natural cycle a soil
that doesn't have animal experiment in
it whether it's birds or deer
or um groundhogs or also the the
millions and trillions of tiny little
entities that are live in healthy soil
all the little worms and beetles and
Tiny Little Critters that you can only
see under the microscope and
bacteria all of
it
excrete and that excrement produces life
providing minerals and nutrients for the
next species that needs to grow there so
garbage removal can also be into that
cycle again of
life that helps us remain
healthy
um so
then the house what nutrients does the
house need does the house need nutrients
well I would say the house
needs beautification you see behind me
in Sylvia's house there are lots of um
framed paintings and things on the wall
there are flowers next to me on the desk
here on the on the table there are lots
of plants in the
house there is a composition of how the
house is arranged all of that
provides a human home as opposed
to a beaver home
or a um termite Hill right so each
species also
requires
that creation
of the real the the environment
for the species and humans
being creative I always maintain that
creativity is what distinguishes us from
the Animal
Kingdom so we want to create an
environment we want to look at something
and rejoice in the beauty of it or be
triggered to be thinking about something
or we want to have Windows where we see
the greenery outside you can't well you
can see it maybe a little bit but it's
too bright out the sun is still
shining
so now we have the house and we
have it has been worn out right the
house I bought is 100 years
old and a little over a hundred years
old and it has been worn out and I am
renovating
in fact I took out the laminate floors
because I discovered that underneath was
beautiful healthy Redwood
floor Red
Oak um so the same can be true for your
body you may have spent the last 10
years eating junk food drinking
alcohol um eating too much sugar
exposing yourself to chemicals in your
makeup and your body products or
sunscreens Etc all of which can put
layers and layers
of laminate
plastic on the inside of your digestive
tract on the inside of your
arteries
and of course on your skin in and on all
your
tissues so to remove that plaque that
chemical layer that you may be wearing
on the inside and on the
outside it
takes that renovation it takes that
removal
unfortunately we have to do the work
with our hands and of course we hire
contractors who are experts in these in
these crafts to remove things in a house
and to reinstall the electricity and to
reinstall the plumbing and to sand down
the floors
Etc and it takes a lot of money and work
and time to renovate an old
house the irony here is not so for our
body for our body our body does most of
the work for us if we give it the right
nutrients relaxation and
environment that is the amazing part and
when I prepared this
whole Mastermind on
renovation that struck me as being the
most amazing thing it is actually faster
to renovate our body than it is to
renovate a
house
because what do we need we need to
cleanse we don't need to go in there
with brushes and and and roam around and
clean and sweep and vacuum and sand down
Etc the body does it all by itself if we
give it the nutrients to do so for
example if we spend seven days on a or
even just five days on a juice or
smoothie
cleanse the body will take down the
plaque on the inside of the arteries the
lymph system will cleanse all the
tissues the the Animas go um the um not
anemas the the the water in your feet
I'm I I'm blanking on the word
will will come back up and be eliminated
your body will do the work because it is
actually a self-healing machine contrary
to the house the house is not a
self-healing machine we've got to do the
work the body on the other hand does it
if you just give it a little bit of
Health what else does it need it needs
the nutrients now of course I will tell
you exactly what the best nutrients are
and when you think about it I think you
can almost get there by yourself too
um it also needs extra oxygen so
breathing deep breathing is very
important exposure to the
outdoors sunshine vitamin D3 production
and of
course in a house on the other other
hand we can produce electricity Now by
putting a solar system on the roof and
we literally absorb and store the
sunshine and use it for our
electricity now our body somehow does
the same but our body just like the
solar system also needs repeated
exposure to the Sun to keep that process
going so um there's another beautiful
parallel if you do not see the sun in
months in a row or cover your face with
hats and your body with
sunscreen you will be
deprived of that healing element and you
will be terribly deprived of
D3 and we know that the Western world is
terribly deficient in vitamin
D3
so why is that important because it
leads to all kinds of
other inabilities of the body to heal
itself when we don't have Sunshine we
don't have oxygen we don't have enough
fluid good water um of course you know
normally I drink out of my high stem
glasses here I just have a high
um a
high
cup and almost like a picture
and I've got spring water in there and
that's what I
pi and it is
delicious so we need the water we need
the nutrients we need the sunshine we
need the
oxygen and we
need
rest not just rest as in good sleep but
we also
need relaxation
deep letting
go so the body can do the work because
when we're tight and the adrenaline is
rushing and we're holding
on we cannot let the body do the work or
the body cannot do the work against your
stress and tightness so therefore in
order to allow the body to do the
cleansing and the last last step I'm
going to talk about last
building so if you do not have the
adequate relaxation whether you do
meditate whether you do deep
relaxation whether you do enough of the
breathing together with letting
go whether you walk in the woods and hug
trees now we actually know that there's
a physical proof of of taking on some of
that tree energy into your body when
under a tree or touching a tree you know
which is hugging a tree
is
so that deep
relaxation is just as important as is
the nutrient because the nutrient will
not get absorbed if you're all tense
inside and if you're all holding your
breath because you're so stressed and
uptight and of course when we're in a
situation like in a house renovation we
tend to be stressed because everything
takes so much longer than you planned
for I can tell you that
story so that
we tend to forget our body when we're in
such a situation right and do not allow
it to get the
relaxation it needs to rebuild itself so
the last thing of the cleansing the
breathing the nourishing the relaxing
and
resting is the building and that's where
the real renovation in the body happens
right of course just as I am rebuilding
my floors repainting the wall wall s um
redoing some of the electricity redoing
some of the plumbing adding extra items
in the bathroom and the
kitchen
that's where the rebuilding of our body
comes in so when we want to rebuild
extra muscle tissue because we want to
be stronger when we want to rebuild
better eyesight so that we don't have to
wear glasses I do I know that I can do
this but you have to take the time and
actually do
it
then what happens we put the nutrients
the relaxation and everything in there
in the beautiful
environment then we begin to build
because that's when the body is able to
build new cell tissue faster and better
of course all of life constantly
rebuilds itself that's what I was trying
not to say earlier because it's of
course the basis of all of life is that
it constantly renews itself cell tissue
has to replicate all the time for
anything to remain alive whether it is a
fruit fly or whether it is an elephant
everything alive or a tree or a
um Forget Me Not or a
bacterium all of it constantly needs to
renew
itself without cell replication there is
no life so how can we get the body to
renew itself of course life does have a
life cycle and I cannot get back to Baby
smooth skin right I have all these
little wrinkles here because I am 71
years old and that shows and that's
okay but these 71 years
old can be used for all that life
experience that I can now
apply that I didn't have before that I
can now apply into what so I want to
build rebuild the tissues as best I can
including the wrinkles and and the
defects that may not be rep
repairable right if for example the
father of my children has the tip of one
of his fingers missing that will not
regrow but the rest of the body can find
ways to work around that missing part I
don't have a muscle tissue on my right
shoulder here it's extremely bony when
you look at it it's just like what is
that why is that so bony and however
much I train it's not possible to put a
muscle there because I was born without
it so there are defects that we all have
that we work around and make everything
else so good that it covers that missing
part that it gets around there like put
a hole in my heart it's just fine I just
need to do extra work I need to go extra
running and walking and working out and
power lifting to make up for that
weakness so that it doesn't become an
impediment all right so we build cell
tissue with the right
nutrients and we can also only do all of
that when we have
what because then you ask why why should
I do all
this why shouldn't I just pop my 101 15
pills you know we I know at my age most
Americans are on at least seven
pills at
least I'm on none
zero
Zill
so why is then the big question
and that's where purpose becomes the
driver you have to have
purpose and I often say to my
clients even if you just have not just
even if your per purpose
is to show the world that you can be fit
and fabulous in your 70s 80s
90s that's purpose enough
but you have to really want it and of
course if you have grandchildren if you
have relatives if you have projects if
you have a book to write oh I came
across
this 86 year old
lady she moved into a senior tiny
house
Community where everybody has creative
projects and where she started a writer
club and they're all writing them all
but you know many people who want to
write their Memoirs and write their
experiences and teach kids if the kids
want to come that's
purpose and of course some of us still
have big
projects what's your project what's your
purpose I was just on the phone last
Sunday with a dear girlfriend of mine
who is Raising and homeschooling her
three grandchildren
and they're fabulous so she became the
teacher and wise
educator guide to her
grandchildren so
that they can have a very special start
on
life um that's
purpose so all of this renovation only
makes sense if there's
purpose and
unfortunately I have never
seen anything
as lacking
purpose as some of the American Homes
I've seen I've lived in Germany in
Norway in Scotland in France in Zimbabwe
in
Namibia in Romania
in well I've visited many other
countries but I have not lived there for
a longer period of time oh Jamaica I
worked
also um and everywhere people seem to
have more
purpose then right
here so ask
yourself what is your purpose you don't
have purpose you won't do the cleansing
you won't even clean your house at seen
terrible American
Homes terribly terribly
sad where every African home as poor as
somebody could be in it could be a crawl
in the mud hut is beautifully
arranged ordained with
designs and kept clean and
orderly so that's what we also need to
do we renovate our house and renovate
our body we need to create order and
cleanliness all right now those who are
just listening in on this when it's on
my YouTube
channel I am currently
offering four week intensives if you do
have a
severe issue like my stroke was if you
do have arthritis or diabetes or you
name it chronic diseases
allergies asthma Etc we can edema that's
the word I was looking for earlier not
enema
[Laughter]
edema okay so edema is water in your
extremities especially in your feet and
and lower legs
but it can also be an edema in your
lungs you know water in your lungs is
pretty dangerous and or in your hands or
joints all together right we just call
it by different names than rheumatoid
arthritis
Etc
so if you need to get out of those kind
of predicaments that your lifestyle has
put you in let's face it
but you can get out of there faster than
you can renovate a house then I offer
for you four week intensives where I'm
on the phone with you or in a zoom call
like this one with you every
day and there is a step by step
cleansing and building process that we
follow to get you out of that
predicament and get you into a lifestyle
that actually supports
a healthy body I've done it many times
with
varying conditions for people or rather
that I have taught people many times how
to do it because it's you yourself of
course who self heals I don't heal you
you heal
yourself very
important
um so there's the Intensive the four
four week
intensive but that of course of course
cost not but that of course
cost some
money and then there is the membership
club that um I just started for the
fitness part the exercise part you know
what I did not talk about exercising
enough because a house doesn't exercise
right but we need to exercise we need to
move tell me what we can compare that to
in a house I guess you know we need to
open and close doors and open and close
windows and those kind of
things
and so that the house inhales and
exhales but we need to exercise and I
have not talked about that sufficient so
in our membership club the fitness over
program that you can join every morning
nine o'clock Eastern on
a zoom
call
um recurring so you just click yourself
in
um is Mondays through Thursdays at 9 o'
in the
morning
and then there are individual
consultations where we discuss what you
most need and that is oh the membership
is only $27 a month so so that is very
affordable and you can get your
exercises in
and meet the other people in the club
and see how
else I can be of
assist and then there are individual
consultations um you can go to johannas
foods.com and find
such and Mary clinked herself out
and you can of
course connect with me at johannas
foods.com and
contact and we will connect with you and
set up
a discovery call which is free where we
can hone in as to what you
need all right so this has been the
preparation for next week's Mastermind
on renovate your
body I hope
that you want to come back and have your
own
questions hi
Mary welcome back but I'm going to close
here please feel free to connect with me
if you want to know
more want to
um want to find out how you can
participate in any of my offerings um I
also do a 12 months course where I teach
you it's a step-by-step process again
how how to be a coach
yourself that's a certificate course and
you get a certificate at the end if you
complete the work required of course
that's the more academic approach to um
elevating your own self to a level of
where you feel confident that you can
share your knowledge that may be very
specific with others and become that
coach and guide for other people who
might want to learn from
you all right this has been the
Mastermind on renovate your
body and part two where I hope that you
will ask all your
questions will be
available next Sunday on September
22nd and I hope to see you there and
many
more all right this has been the
Mastermind I'm Professor Johanna sopia
you find me on YouTube um my channel is
oh just Google Prof Johanna Sophia for
Professor Johanna Sophia and you will
probably find the YouTube channel the
Facebook the Instagram the LinkedIn the
all those pages the Tik Tok which I
guess Google doesn't show you readily
right but I am on Tik Tok actually quite
active on Tik
Tok
and and you'll find interviews where I'm
interviewing people or where I'm being
interviewed Etc so johannas foods.com
however is the main website
and you can connect with me on the
contact page there and I look forward to
talking with you
[Music]